A Guide to the Nourse Family Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Nourse Family Papers 1751-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3490-a
153 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 3490 was originally deposited in the library by Constance and Charlotte Nourse, Fauquier County, Va., 1950 June 21. It was purchased by the Library, 1950 August 15.
Accession 3490-a was deposited in the library by Constance and Charlotte Nourse, Fauquier County, Va., 1951 June 21.
Scope and Content
31 manuscript volumes and ca. 1400 manuscripts of the Nourse family of Weston, Herfordshire, England; Berkeley County, W. Va.; Washington, D.C.; and Weston, Fauquier County, Va.; and of related Bull and Morris families.
The collection includes: letters, account books, commonplace books, day books, notebooks, ledgers, maps, music, newspaper clippings, sermons, recipe book, journals, and other family records.
The diary, 1846, 1850-1851, of James Burn Nourse describes an overland journey west, voyage around Cape Horn on the U.S. sloop of war "Preble", and his experiences in the California gold rush.
Ledgers, 1844-1848, record operations of a foundry, possibly the West Point Foundry, West Point, N.Y.
Ledgers of Joseph Nourse and letters to his wife, Maria Bull Nourse and his son, Charles Josephus Nourse chiefly relate to American finance during the Revolutionary and Confederation periods, his work as Register of the Treasury, campaigns in the War of 1812, the administration of the U.S. Army, 1819-1829, the effect of Jackson's spoils system; and to the Washington political and social scene and include mentions of James and Dolley Madison.
Letters of Charles Josephus Nourse to his wife, Rebecca Morris Nourse and others, describe life in London where he had been sent by Madison, the War of 1812, military actions, and Indian removals.
Letters from Anthony Morris to his children describe his life as an unofficial diplomat in Spanish society, his travels in Spain and personal matters.
In addition the papers contain correspondence of other family members.
Individual items of interest include a 1780 broadside regarding General Lafayette's orders regarding the proposed invasion of Canada, a note regarding entertainment for General Lafayette, and James Barbour's map of Washington, D.C.; a dinner invitation from George Washington; two dinner invitations from James Madison; three pieces of colonial Maryland currency, 1775-1776.
Correspondents include Nicholas Biddle, John C. Calhoun, Sir Augustus John Foster, Sam Houston, Joel Poinsett, Richard Rush, and Winfield Scott.
Contents List
- Letters and documents concerning James Nourse and Joseph Burton., 1751-1754 (Box 1)
- Joseph Burton to James Woodpoofe; Bill for Lucas funeral, 1755 Sept. 10 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of James and Robert Nourse, Charles Fouace., 1770-1779 (Box 1)
- Broadside - General Lafayette's Order re proposed invasion of Canada., 1780 (Box 1)
- Nourse and Fouace family letters; Genealogical data on the Nourse family., 1782-1783 (Box 1)
- Documents on estate of Joseph Nourse., 1784 (Box 1)
- Invitations and Scrapbook contents from Washington, Madison, etc., 1784-1848 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Joseph Nourse and Maria (Bull) Nourse., 1784-1789 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other papers of John, Joseph and Maria Nourse., 1792-1796 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Joseph Nourse, 1796-1799 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous., ante. 1800 (Box 1)
- Letters to Joseph Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1800-1802 (Box 1)
- Letters of Joseph Nourse and Maria Nourse, also Phoebe Morris., 1803-1804 (Box 1)
- A. Foster to Charles Nourse., 1805 Jan. (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Joseph, Charles J., and Maria Nourse., 1805 (Box 1)
- Letters of Charles J. Nourse and J. Bull., 1806-1807 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Joseph and Charles J. Nourse, Phoebe Morris., 1808 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Joseph and Charles J. Nourse., 1809 (Box 1)
- Nourse correspondence., 1800-1809 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph Nourse and S. H. Young., 1810 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of S. H. Young, Joseph, J. B. Nourse and A. Morris., 1811 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph Nourse., Jan.-April 1812 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph Nourse and S. H. Young., May -Aug. 1812 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris and Joseph Nourse., Sept.-Dec. 1812 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph, J. B. and C. J. Nourse., Jan.-Apr. 1813 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, J. B. and Joseph Nourse., May-Aug. 1813 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Joseph,Nourse., Sept.-Dec. 1813 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. and Phoebe Morris and Joseph Nourse., Jan.-Apr. 1814 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph and C. J. Nourse., May-Aug. 1814 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph and Maria Nourse., Sept.-Dec. 1814 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, L. H. Lloyd and Joseph Nourse., Jan.-Apr. 1815 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph Nourse and L. H. Lloyd., May-Aug. 1815 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, Joseph Nourse and L. H. Lloyd., Sept.-Dec. 1815 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of L. H. Lloyd, Anthony Morris, Rosa and James Nourse., Jan.-June 1816 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of A. Morris, C. J. and Joseph Nourse., July-Dec.1816 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Joseph and C. J. Nourse and P. P. Morris., 1817 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of L. H. Lloyd and Joseph Nourse., 1818 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of J. H. Lloyd and C. J. Nourse., 1819 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of S. H. Young, Joseph and C. J. Nourse., ca. 1810-1820 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of C. J., Joseph and Rebecca Nourse., ca. 1820-1830 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Joseph and C. J. Nourse, 1820-1822; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Diary unsigned - chiefly sermons., 1823 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Joseph Nourse., 1823 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Charles Nourse., 1824 (Box 2)
- N[icholas] Biddle to Joseph Nourse., 1825 May 25 (Box 2)
- Sam Houston to Maj. C. J. Nourse., 1825 July 28 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Joseph and C. J. Nourse., 1825 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse as Adjutant General., 1825 (Box 3)
- Richard Rush to Maj. Nourse., 1826 June 7 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse., 1826 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1827 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. and Joseph Nourse., 1828 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse., 1829 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. and Rebecca Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1830 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse., ca. 1830-1840 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. and Rebecca Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1831 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Rebecca Nourse., 1832 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Rebecca and Joseph Nourse., 1833 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Joseph Nourse and Anthon Morris., 1834 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Anthony Morris and Caroline Nourse., 1835 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse., 1836 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. and Rebecca Nourse., 1837 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J., Caroline and Joseph Nourse., 1838 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse and Anthony Nourse., 1839 (Box 3)
- Osmond Peters to Joel R. Poinsett., 1840 Dec. 22 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. and Rosa Nourse., 1840 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Charles and James Nourse., ca. 1840-1850 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J., Mary and James Nourse., 1841 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J., Mary and Rosa Nourse., 1842 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Rosa, Carolina and C. J. Nourse., 1843 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Mary and C. J. Nourse and Eliza., 1844 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J. and J. Burn Nourse., 1845 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of J. B. and C. J. Nourse., 1846 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Anthony Morris and J. B. and C. J. Nourse., 1847 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of J. Pemberton, C. J. and Rosa Nourse., 1848 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of C. J., C. J., Jr., J. B. and Eliza Nourse., 1849 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. J., Pemberton, J. B. Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1850 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. J., J. B., Rosa and Henrietta Nourse., 1851 (Box 4)
- Papers re estate of C. J. Nourse - See also notebooks of C. J., Jr. regarding this subject., 1851 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Anthony Morris, J. B., and C. J. Nourse., 1852 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of J. Pemberton Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1853 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. J. and Rosa Nourse - Accounts., 1854 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa and J. B. Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1855 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of J. B. Nourse and S. Morris Accounts., 1856 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1857 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa, J. B. and C. J. Nourse, Jr., 1858 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of J. B. and C. J. Nourse., 1859 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Pemberton, Joseph, Rosa and Caroline Nourse., ca. 1850-1860 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of J. B., Pem, C. J. and Henrietta Nourse., 1860 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. J., J. B., Pem, and Rosa Nourse., 1861 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa, B. J., and Henrietta Nourse and Anthony Morris., 1862 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Henrietta Nourse and Elizabeth Simms., 1863 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Henrietta and C. J. Nourse and E. Simms., 1864 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa, Henrietta and Caroline Nourse., 1865 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Charley and May., 1866 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa Nourse., 1867 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Charley., 1868 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. J. Nourse, Jr., ca. 1860-1870 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Mrs. Nourse., ca. 1870-1880 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa Nourse., 1870 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. W. Simms., 1871 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of C. W. Simms and Phoebe Chaderton., 1872 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Rosa Nourse., 1874-1878 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous correspondence and photographs., 1880-1900 (Box 5)
- Constance Nourse to "Walt"., 1918 June 20 (Box 5)
- Winfield Scott to C. J. Nourse., n. d. (Box 5)
- Obituary of wife of General John Bull (Mrs. Mary Bull)., n. d. (Box 5)
- Correspondence, ca. 300 items, 5 folders. (Box 5)
- Commonplace Book - Joseph Burton., 1685 (Box 6)
- Wastebook - Joseph Nourse., 1773-1782 (Box 6)
- Commonplace Book ot Joseph Burton., 17th c. (Box 6)
- Journal., 1778-1803 (Box 7)
- Journal - [Joseph] Nourse., 1781 (Box 7)
- Journal - James Nourse Estate., 1792-1799 (Box 7)
- Ledger., 1800-1816 (Box 7)
- Book of Sermons - James B. Nourse., 1790-1838 (Box 8)
- Journal., 1805-1818 (Box 8)
- Ledger., 1811-1825 (Box 8)
- Commonplace book., 1754-1842 (Box 9)
- Music book., [1815] (Box 9)
- Account book., 1826-1828 (Box 9)
- Account book., 1837-1840 (Box 9)
- Ledger., [1794-1815] (Box 10)
- Account book., 1820-1821 (Box 10)
- Daybook., 1825-1835 (Box 10)
- Notebook of C. I. Nourse re Estate of Father., 1851 March 22 (Box 10)
- Newspaper clippings., 1861 (Box 10)
- Account book., 1863-1865 (Box 10)
- Scrapbook of C. I. Nourse., 1904-1905 (Box 10)
- James Barbours' map of Washington, D. C. (Box 10)
- Recipe Book., n. d. (Box 10)
- Special Military Maps., n. d. (Box 10)
- Commonplace book., 1790-1830 (Box 11)
- Account book., 1844-1848, 1868-1876 (Box 11)
- Diary and Account book., 1851 (Box 11)
- Diary and Letter book., 1854-1858 (Box 11)
- Notebook - James B. Nourse., 1856 (Box 11)
- Daybook., 1864-1868 (Box 11)
- Notebook - James B. Nourse., 1870 (Box 11)
- Scrapbook of Susan E. Fallon., 1892-1901 (Box 11)
- Commonplace book., 1790 (Box 12)
- Receipt book., 1817-1821 (Box 12)
- Account book., 1819-1822 (Box 12)
- Receipt book., 1821-1824 (Box 12)
- Letter book and Scrapbook., 1823-1870 (Box 12)
- Notebook - R. M. Nourse., 1834-1835 (Box 12)
- Scrapbook - Henrietta C. Nourse., 1851 (Box 12)
- Check book., 1851-1856 (Box 12)
- Check book., 1854-1860 (Box 12)
- Printed material., 1865-1890 (Box 12)
- Waltzes., n. d. (Box 12)